Guide to the Catharine T. Patterson Collection of Walter Crane
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Writings and Graphic Material, 1867–1913; Series II; 13.43; 10 boxes + 1 Broadside oversize
  - Printed Material
    - Independent Order of Odd Fellows, Manchester Unity Friendly Society, 1904, 1909 (Box 6 (Oversize), Folder 93)
      Large copy of past provincial grand master certificate engraved by Emery Walker, with two copies of the society's 1909 calendar.
    - Independent Labour Party, 1895 (Box 9, Folder 109)
      Handbill for first Socialist carnival.
    - International School conducted by Louise Michel, circa 1892 (Box 9, Folder 110)
      Proof print of prospectus cover.
    - Jeffrey & Co., undated (Box 4, Folder 67)
      Advertisement for artistic wallpapers.
    - Joseph Hughes, undated (Box 4, Folder 68)
      Proof print of Hughes's Educational Catalogue cover.
    - Lyceum Theatre Shakespearean Season, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 69)
      Two printed programs.
    - New Year's Card, circa 1879 (Box 9, Folder 111)
      Folding card with folding envelope, designed for Marcus Ward & Co.
    - The Pioneer, 1886 (Box 4, Folder 70)
      Proof of contents page for journal.
    - Scottish Widows' Fund Life Assurance Fund, 1913, undated (Box 4, Folder 71)
      Three bookmarks and one proof print of the logo.
    - The Story of the Glittering Plain or the Land of Living Men (Hammersmith: Kelmscott Press, 1894) (Box 4, Folder 72)
      Proof pages of page 50 (Chapter VIII) and page 84 (Chapter XIII).
    - Walter Crane's Baby's Own Alphabet, 1893 (Box 4, Folder 73)
      Copy with damaged cover and tape repairs.
  - Other Material
    - Portrait photograph of Crane by Elliott Fry, London, circa 1880 (Box 4, Folder 74)
      Cabinet card format, autographed by Crane.
    - Textiles
      - Silk damask pouch with embroidered butterfly, undated (Box 4, Folder 75)
      - Satin album cover with petit-point design, undated (Box 12, Folder 115)
      - "Strawberry Thief" fabric, made by Morris and Company, circa 1883 (Box 12, Folder 116-118)
        Six pieces of indigo-discharged and block-printed cotton designed and manufactured by William Morris; connection to Crane unknown.
      - "Diana" fan, undated (Box 13)
        Design painted in silver on a black silk fan
      - Batik-dyed linen portfolio cover, undated (Box 6 (Oversize), Folder 94)
- Catharine T. Patterson Collection Files, 1920–1957; Series III; 0.42; 1 box
  The series holds material that documents Catharine T. Patterson's collection and her interest in Crane.
  - Correspondence, 1920–1956 (Box 5, Folder 76)
    Letters to Catharine T. Patterson and her brother Chauncey Brewster Tinker from borrowing institutions, dealers, and colleagues; also present are invoices for some collection items.
  - A Bibliography of First Editions of Books Illustrated by Walter Crane, by Gertrude Masse (London: Chelsea Publishing Co., 1923) (Box 5, Folder 77)
    With annotations throughout by Patterson; at the back are her autograph notes on the original drawings in her collection and a inventory listing collection items numbered 1-21.
  - Collection inventory sheets, undated (Box 5, Folder 78)
    Typscript and autograph manuscript, listing item numbered 43-68.
  - Catalog cards for collection, A-Z by title, undated (Box 5, Folder 79-81)
    Primarily documents some of her book collection.
  - Material related to Patterson collection exhibitions, 1939, 1946, undated (Box 5, Folder 82)
  - Research materials
    - Notes on Crane, undated (Box 5, Folder 83)
    - Library call slips, undated (Box 5, Folder 84)
    - Catalogue of a Collection of Designs by Walter Crane (Boston: Museum of Fine Arts, 1891) (Box 5, Folder 85)
    - Tear sheets with Crane illustrations, 1891–1898 (Box 5, Folder 86)
    - Clippings and catalogues, 1892–1956 (Box 5, Folder 87)
      Includes material about Crane and children's literature.
    - Clippings, 1928, 1942 (Box 9, Folder 113)
      Material on children's literature.
    - Clippings, 1942 (Box 9, Folder 114)
      Material on the Newport tower.
    - "My Grandfather Walter Crane," by Anthony Crane, 1957 January (Box 5, Folder 88)
      In Yale University Library Gazette 31, no. 3 (January 1957): 97-109.
  - Writings
    - "Pre-Raphaelites and Labor," by Chauncey Brewster Tinker, 1922 July 29 (Box 5, Folder 89)
      Essay in The Literary Review (July 29, 1922).
    - "Walter Crane," by C. T. P. and C. B. T., 1924 January (Box 5, Folder 90)
      Essay by Catharine T. Patterson and Chauncey Brewster Patterson in The Brooklyn Museum Quarterly 11, no. 1 (January 1924): 1-7.
    - "A Walter Crane Collection," by Catharine Tinker Patterson, 1941 July 26 (Box 6 (Oversize), Folder 95)
      Essay in the Christian Science Monitor (July 26, 1941) about how Patterson began to collect Crane.